<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of, by the Church Wardens and Swornemen within the Archdeaconrie of Middlesex And the trueth thereof to be by them vpon their oathes certainely presented to M. Doctor Squier Archdeacon there or to his officialles, with particular aunsweare to euerie article. 1582.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1582</title>
            <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Middlesex. Archdeacon (1557-1588 : Squier)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847119</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of, by the Church Wardens and Swornemen within the Archdeaconrie of Middlesex And the trueth thereof to be by them vpon their oathes certainely presented to M. Doctor Squier Archdeacon there or to his officialles, with particular aunsweare to euerie article. 1582.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1582</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Middlesex. Archdeacon (1557-1588 : Squier)</author>
                  <author>Squier, Adam, d. 1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling at the signe of the Fox in Old Fishstreate neere the signe of the Swanne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12132:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12132:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES TO BE ENQVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED OF, BY THE <hi>Church Wardens and Swornemen</hi> within the Archdeaconrie of Middleſex;</p>
            <p>And the trueth thereof to be by them vpon their oathes certainely preſented to <hi>M. Doctor Squier</hi> Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con there or to his Officialles, with particular aunſweare to euerie Article.</p>
            <p>1582.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>¶VBIQVE FLORESCIT.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling at the Signe of the Fox in Old Fiſhſtreate néere the Signe of the Swanne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:12132:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12132:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ARTICLES TO BE ENQVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED OF, BY THE CHVRCHWARDENS and Swornemen within the Archdeaconrie of Middleſex: and the trueth therof to be by them vpon their oathes, certainely preſented to M. Doctor SQVIER Archdeacon there, or to his Officials, with particular aunſweare to euerie Article. <hi>Anno Domini 1582.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, whether Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer be ſaid in your Church or Chappell vpon the Sondayes and Holye dayes at conuenient houres reuerently and diſtinctly in ſuche order, without anye kinde of alteration, as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by the Booke of Common Prayer, and the Lawes of this Realme? and whether your Miniſter ſo tourne himſelfe, and ſtand in ſuch place of your Church or Chauncell, as the people may beſt heare the ſame? Whether the Holy Sacramentes be likewiſe miniſtred reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in ſuch manner as by the Lawes of this Realme is appoynted? And, whether vpon Wedniſdayes and Fridayes, not being Holy dayes, the Letanye and other Prayers appointed for the daye, be ſayde accordingly, and the Excommunication againſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, read thriſe yearely?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12132:3"/>
            <p n="2">2 Whether you haue in your Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all thinges neceſſary and requiſite for common prayer and adminiſtration of the Sacramentes, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the booke of Common Prayer with the new Kalender, two Pſalters, the Engliſhe Bible in the largeſt volume, the two Tomes of the Homelies, the Paraphraſis of Eraſmus tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, the Table of the Tenne Commaundementes, the Table for the degrees of Matrimonie, a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Pulpit well placed: a comely and decent Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtanding on a frame, for the Holy Communion, with a fayre linnen cloth to laye vpon the ſame, and ſome coueringe of Silke, Buckerame, or other ſuch like, for the cleane keeping therof, a fayre and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion Cup of Siluer and a couer of ſiluer for the ſame, a ſure Cofer wyth two lockes for the keeping of the Regiſter Booke, and a ſtrong Cheſt or box for the Almes of the poore?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether any perſon or perſons bee admitted to aunſweare as Godfathers or Godmothers at the Chriſtening of any Childe, except he or ſhe haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receiued the Holy Communion, and can geue accompte of their Faith, and will recite the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſter, if he or ſhe be thereunto required?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether any perſon or perſons, not beinge ordered at the leaſt for a Deacon, do either ſay Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer openly in your church, ſolemnize Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, or adminiſter the Sacrament of Baptiſme, or deliuer to the Communicantes the Lordes Cup, at the celebration of the Holye Communion, or doe burie the deade, or geue Thankes for Women after
<pb facs="tcp:12132:3"/>
their Childbirth, and what he or they be that ſo doe?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Farmer of your Benefice, do cauſe any Curate to ſerue in your Church before hee be examined and admitted by the Ordinarie, or his Deputie in writing, and your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter haue his ſufficient letter of Orders or no?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether your Miniſter or you haue ſuffred any Interludes to bee played in your Churche or Chappell, where Gods Word and Prayer are to be vſed, or there be any in your Pariſh that doth violate or breake the Lordes Day by any kinde of worke or paſtime whatſoeuer, or any Minſtrels that vſe anye playinge vpon their Inſtrumentes in your Churche or Chappell, or your Churchyard, or other that hath made any fray, or vſed any brawlinge or vnſeemely noyſe there, or any that vſe any Dauncinge or other kinde of vayne paſtime in the foreſaide places at any time, And whether ther be any Dauncing, Rifling, or gameplaying, or any bodily labour, as ploughing, carting, or any handie crafte vſed in your Pariſh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſolemne Feaſtes, or Feſtiuall dayes?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether the people of your Pariſh, eſpecially houſholders hauing no lawfull excuſe to bee abſente, do faithfullye and diligentlye endeuor themſelues to reſort with their children and ſeruantes to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe Churche or Chappell on the Holy dayes, and chiefly vpon the Sondayes, to Morninge and Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge Prayer, and vpon reaſonable let thereof, to ſome vſuall place where Common Prayer is vſed, and then and there abide orderlye, and ſoberlye, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:12132:4"/>
the time of Common Prayer, Homelies, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinges, and other Seruice of Gods word there v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, reuerently and deuoutly giuinge themſelues to the hearing thereof, and who they be that either ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligentlye or willfully abſente themſelues, or come very late to Church vpon the Sondayes eſpeciallye, or that walke, talke, or otherwiſe vnreuerentlye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues in the Church, or vſe any gaminge abroade or in anye houſe, or ſitte in the ſtreates or churchyarde, or in anie Tauerne, or Alehouſe vpon the Sonday or other Holy day, in the time of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, Sermons or reading of the Homilies, either before noone or after noone, or els reſorte to Faires, Playes, or games, in the ſame time?</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether the forfaiture of twelue pence for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſuche offence appoynted by a Statute made in the firſt yeare of the Queenes Maieſties raigne be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied, and taken by the Church Wardens of euerye perſon that offendeth, and by them bee put to the vſe of the poore of the Pariſh, and if it bee not, by whoſe default it is not leuied, and what particular ſommes of mony haue bene forfayted that way, &amp; by whome ſince the Annuntiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lady in the year of our Lord 1581. vntill the day of geuing vp the preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerninge theſe articles, and to whome ſuch forfaitures haue beene deliuered?</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether there bee anye Innekeepers, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues, Vittaylers, or Tiplers that ſuffer or admit anye perſon or perſons in their houſes to eate or drinke, or play at Cards, Tables or ſuch like games in time of Common Prayer or Sermon on Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes
<pb facs="tcp:12132:4"/>
or Holy dayes, and whether there bee anye ſhoppes open on Sondayes or Holy dayes, or anye Butchers or others that commonly vſe to ſell meate or other thinges in the tyme of Common Prayer, Preaching, or readinge of the Homilies. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any Faires or common markets falling vpon the Holy dayes, there be any ſhewing of any wares before the deuine ſeruice be done.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether for the putting of the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and ſwornemen the better in remembrance of their duetie in obſeruing and noting ſuch as offende in not comming to diuine ſeruice, your Miniſter doe openly euerie Sonday, after he haue read the ſecond Leſſon at Morning and Euening Prayer, moniſhe and warne the Churchwardens and Swornemen to looke to their charge in this behalfe, and to obſerue who contrarie to the ſaide Statute, offende in abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues from their Pariſh Church, or vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently as is aforeſaide vſe themſelues in the tyme of diuine ſeruice?</p>
            <p n="11">11 Whether your Miniſter do exerciſe himſelfe in godlye ſtudie of Holy Scriptures, and vertuous bringing vp of youth, as in teaching of the Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſme laſtlye ſetfoorth by authoritie, and other godlye exerciſes from time to time?</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether your Miniſter do at the leaſt euery Sonday and Holy day, openly in the Church cal for, heare and inſtruct, all the Children, Apprentiſes and ſeruantes of both the ſexes, that be of conuenient age within your Pariſh, or at the leaſt ſo many of them,
<pb facs="tcp:12132:5"/>
as the time will ſerue, and as he may well heare and inſtruct, for halfe an houre at the leaſt before, or at the Eueninge Prayer, in the X. Commaundementes, the Articles of the beleefe, and the Lordes Prayer, and diligently examine and teach them the ſaide Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme?</p>
            <p n="13">13 Whether all Fathers, Mothers, Maiſters and Dames of your Pariſhe, cauſe their Children, Seruauntes, and Apprentiſes, both mankinde and womankinde, beinge aboue ſixe yeares of age, to come to the Churche on the Sondayes and Holye dayes, at the time to them appoynted, or at the leaſt ſuch and ſo many of them as your Miniſter ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, and obediently to heare and be ordered by the Miniſter vntill ſuche tyme as they haue learned the ſame Catechiſme? And what be the names of theſe that doe not cauſe their Children, Seruauntes and Apprentiſes ſo to come to the Churche to bee inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and examined? And how many of the ſaid Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Seruants, and Apprentiſes be in your Pariſh, which being aboue ſeauen yeares olde, doe not aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare to the ſayde Catechiſme, and what bee their names and age, and wyth whom they dwell? And whether do you which are the Church Wardens di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlye obſerue the offenders in the premiſſes, that you may quarterly make true preſentment of them?</p>
            <p n="14">14 Whether your Miniſter, or any man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in your Pariſh doe willfully mainetaine or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende any Hereſie, falſe opinions, Popiſhe errours, contrarye to the lawes of Almightie God, and true doctrine, by publike authoritie in thys Realme now
<pb facs="tcp:12132:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſetfoorth? And whether any keepe any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Conuenticles, contrarye to the Lawes, or anye within your Pariſh be ſuſpected to bee Papiſtes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtes, Libertines, or of the deteſtable ſecte of the Familie of Loue, or of any other notable hereſie, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether, doth your Parſon, Vicar, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, or Miniſter keepe any ſuſpected woman in hys houſe, or bee an incontinent perſon, geuen to dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, idlenes, or be a haunter of Tauernes, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, or ſuſpected places, or be a Hunter, Hawker, Dicer, Carder, Tabler, Swearer, Falſe diſſembler, or otherwiſe ſuſpected of any notorious crime, or giue any euill example of life?</p>
            <p n="16">16 Whether your Churche bee voide of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent, how long it hath bene ſo voide, by whome, and at whoſe order the fruites are gathered, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, by whome and at whoſe appointmente the cure is ſerued?</p>
            <p n="17">17 Whether your Miniſter vſe to praye for the Quéenes moſte excellente Maieſtie (Quéene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth) in your Church: and whether hee exhorte the people to obedience of her Highnes, and other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates béeing in authoritie vnder her, or no?</p>
            <p n="18">18 Whether your Parſon or Vicar hath prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched or cauſed to bee preached in your Churche his quarterly or monethly Sermons, as by the Quéenes Iniunctions hee is bounde, and what bée the names of him or them, that ſo did preache, and whether hée
<pb facs="tcp:12132:6"/>
admitted any to preach, not béeing lawfully licenced, or haue letted or inhibited thoſe that were licenced, and whether if there be no Sermon, your Miniſter doe reade euery Sonday diſtinctly and plainely ſome part of the Homelies appointed by the Quéenes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to be read? And whether doth he Quarterly read the Iniunctions?</p>
            <p n="19">19 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, haue publikely, or ſecreatly taught any doctrine ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the diſcredite of the receiued order, for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernemente or publike Prayer, in the Churche, or make anye innouation? and whether they haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any man ſo teaching or making any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation, who they bée and what bée their names, that ſo did teach?</p>
            <p n="20">20 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, after the Goſpell, haue read openly in your Churche twiſe this yeare plainely without addition or change the declaration of certain principall Articles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſetforth by both the Archbiſhops &amp; the Biſhops of this Realme, for vnitie of doctrine, being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee read vpon ſome Sonday within one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth next after Michaelmas and Eaſter yearely?</p>
            <p n="21">21 Whether your Miniſter hath admitted to the receiuing of the holy Communion any open and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious ſinner or euill liuer, by whome the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is offended, or anye malicious perſon that is out of charitie, or that hath done any open wrong to his neighbors, by woord or déede, without due pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, firſt done, or reconciliation had, to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb facs="tcp:12132:6"/>
of the congregation?</p>
            <p n="22">22 Whether your Miniſter hath admitted to the holy Communion any of his Pariſh either man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde or womankinde, that cannot ſay by hart the X. Commaundementes, the Articles of the Faith, and the Lordes Prayer, and that cannot ſay by hart the Catechiſme authorized, or are not diligente to learne, to render a reaſon of their Faith, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he marry any perſons which were ſingle before, that cannot ſay the ſayde Cathechiſme, and whether he vſeth to examine hys Pariſhners at conueniente times, to the entent he may know whether they can ſay the ſame which is required, and whether there be any that do refuſe ſo to be examined or no?</p>
            <p n="23">23 Whether there bee any in your Pariſh man or woman beinge of conueniente age, that hath not receiued, the holy Communion thriſe at the leaſt this laſt yeare, and namely at Eaſter laſt or there about, and what their names are? And whether yearelye before Eaſter or at ſuch conueniente times as your Miniſter ſhall thinke méete, and require hys Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners to recite vnto hym the Catechiſme by harte in Engliſhe, if any doe willfully and ſtubbernely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to recite the ſame, the Church Wardens and Swornemen or any of them doe aſsiſte and aide the Miniſter therein, that ſuche ſtubberne perſons maye bee rebuked and repelled, from the Communion at that time?</p>
            <p n="24">24 Whether there bee in your Pariſh any that are known or ſuſpected to be malicious, contentious
<pb facs="tcp:12132:7"/>
or vncharitable perſons, anye ſwearer, or blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the name of God, anye fornicators, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, inceſtuous perſons, baudes, or anye that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſuch incontinente perſons, or anye that harbor women with child which be vnmaried, conueying or ſufferinge them to goe awaye before they haue done anye pennance, or make ſatisfaction to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or any perſons that are vehemently ſuſpected of any of theſe or ſuche like faultes, or that bee not of good name and fame touching ſuch crimes, whether there bee in your Pariſh any dronkardes, common ſlaunderers of their neighbors, raylers, skoldes, or ſowers of diſcorde betwene neighbors, either baudes or any other euill or ſuſpected liuers of incontinente life, who they be?</p>
            <p n="25">25 Whether the Schoolemaſters or Schoolemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes that teach in your Pariſhe, either openly or priuately in anye gentlemans houſe or others bée of good and ſincere Religion and conuerſation, and bée diligent in the teachinge of youth in the Catechiſme laſtly ſetfoorth by authoritie, as alſo in other godlye and neceſſary documents of learning, whether they bee examined, allowed and licenced to teach by the Ordinary or his deputie, and what bee their names that be not licenced?</p>
            <p n="26">26 Whether there be any that be maried in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées forbidden, or that haue married two wiues or two husbandes both liuing, or that liue not together with their wiues, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="27">27 Whether there bee anye man or woman in
<pb facs="tcp:12132:7"/>
your Pariſh that vſeth witchcraft, coniuring, ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying, charmes, or vnlawfull Prayers or inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Latin or Engliſh for or vpon any Chriſtian bodie, or beaſt, and what be their names, or any that do go or ſéeke for helpe at ſuch ſorcerers handes?</p>
            <p n="28">28 Whether you doe know, or haue heard ſay, that within your Pariſhe there is, or are any perſon or perſons notoriouſlye knowen or ſuſpected, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend contrary to the Statute made in the ſeauen and thirtie yeare of the raigne of King Henrye the eight for reformation of vſurie, and reuiued by an Acte made in the thirtéenth yeare of the raigne of the Quéenes Maieſtie?</p>
            <p n="29">29 Whether your Miniſter do Church any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married women, after they haue béene deliuered of their children begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnlawfully, before they haue acknowledged their faultes openly, according to the order preſcribed by the Ordinarie or his deputie?</p>
            <p n="30">30 Whether your Fontes or Baptiſteries bee remooued from the place where they were wonte to ſtande, or any perſons leauinge the vſe of them, doe Chriſten or Baptize in Baſons, or other prophane veſſels, not accuſtomablie vſed in the Church before time? And whether any Chriſten without Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Godmothers, or after any other order then is preſcribed, by the booke of Common Prayer?</p>
            <p n="31">31 Whether your Church, Chappel, or Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and euerie parte thereof be all in good and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reparations, and cleanely kepte, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:12132:8"/>
houſe of your Parſon and Vicar with the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings thereunto belonginge, likewiſe repaired, and your Churchyarde well fenced and cleanely kepte, and if any of the ſame bee ruinous and in decay, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row whoſe default it is ſo? And whether the Church Wardens of the laſte yeare were enioyned to haue repaired any part of the Church or fenced the Church yard and did neglect to do the ſame?</p>
            <p n="32">32 Whether the Church Wardens of the laſte yeare haue geuen to the Pariſh a iuſt accompt of the Church goodes, that were committed to their charge, and what Church goods they haue ſold, and whether to the profite of the Churche or no, or anye that doe withholde anye ſtocke or money belonginge to the Churche? And whether anye perſon ſuppreſſe the laſt will of the deade, and perfourme not Legacies bequeathed to the Churche or to Orphanes, poore maides marriages, high wayes, ſchooles, or any other godly vſe?</p>
            <p n="33">33 Whether when any chriſtian body is in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge, the Bell be tolled, eſpecially in great Townes where they be néere the Church or Chappell, ſo that the people maye bee moued thereby to praye for the ſicke perſon, and whether there bee any other vaine ringing but one ſhort peale before the buriall and an other after?</p>
            <p n="34">34 Whether your Miniſter doe kéepe well and orderly your Regiſter booke of Weddinges, Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, and Burialles within your Pariſh, and doe preſent a copie of them once euerie yeare, by Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:12132:8"/>
to the Ordinarie or his Officers?</p>
            <p n="35">35 Whether there bee within your Pariſh any euill diſpoſed perſons whiche haue by anye meanes vnreuerently abuſed your Miniſter, either by worde or déede?</p>
            <p n="36">36 Whether there bée any within your Pariſh, that haue béene preſented as offenders heretofore, which haue not done their pennance preſcribed vnto them, or that ſtand willfullie excommunicated, and who they be?</p>
            <p n="37">37 Whether you know or haue heard that the Church Wardens and Sworne men of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the laſt yeare haue left any perſon or perſons pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable for any offence by the Lawes Eccleſiaſtical vnpreſented, whereby they haue eſcaped vnrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and by whoſe default, and what are the parties names that haue ſo offended, and wherein haue they offended?</p>
            <p n="38">38 Finally, whether you know or vnderſtand of any other matter or cauſe Eccleſiaſticall woorthy of preſentmente, herein not expreſſed, and you ſhall preſent the ſame?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
